The Life Of Muhammad ﷺ, Madinan Period Volume 2
By Imam Anwar Al_Awlaki,
اَعُوْذُ بِاللهِ مِنَّ الشِّيْطَانِ الرَّجِيْمِ ۝ بِسْمِ اللهِ الرَّحْمَانِ الرَّحِيْمَ۝
اَلْحَمْدُ لله ، وَالصَّلَاةُ وَالسَّلَامُ عَلى سَيِّدِنَا محمد
وَعَلَى اَلِهِ وَصَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًا كَثِيْرا
اَلسَّلَامُ عَلَيْكُمْ وَرَحْمةُ الله وَبَرَكَاتُه
Another Sariyyah(سرية) and the important part of it is the story of Muhallim Bin Jassama(محلم بن جثامة).
Muhallim Bin Jassama(محلم بن جثامة) was a Muslim in this Sariyyah(سرية).
They were traveling and a man called Aamir Bin Azbat al-Ashjaee(عامر بن عضبط ألأشجعي) pass them by
and when he pass by he said, Assalam O Alaikum(السلام عليكم)!
This is the greeting of Muslims.
Muhallim Bin Jassama(محلم بن جثامة) rushes out and kills this man.
This man who just gave them Salaam(سلام), he went and killed him
because he knew him from the time of Jahilliyah(جاهلية) and there was a problem between them,
so he sought revenge, even though the man said, Assalam O Alaikum(السلام عليكم).
So, the chief of the tribe of the murdered came to Rasool Allah ﷺ, Oyeyna Bin Badr(عيينه بن بدر).
And he's asking for the blood for retribution.
And the chief of the tribe of Muhallim(محلم), also came to Rasool Ullah, Al-Aqra'a Bin Habis(اَلْأقْرَاع بن حابس)
asking Rasool Allah ﷺ leniency.
Rasool Allah ﷺ wants to prevent Fitnah(فِتْنَه) from occurring between these two tribes,
and because it's a feudal society, the Society of Arabia.
So Rasool Allah ﷺ wants(to prevent Fitnah), because in the situation like this, it's Qatl Amd(قتل عمد).
There are two options,
the two options are given to the Oulea(أولياء) of the deceased.
The family members of the deceased
they can choose between asking for the execution of the one who murdered,
or accepting the blood money which is 100 camels.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ wants to convince them to accept the blood money, in order to prevent the Fitnah(فِتْنَه).
Oyeyna Bin Badr(عيينه بن بدر) said;
لَا وَلله
In the name of Allah.
لَا اَعْدَآئه حَتَّى اُضِيْقَ نِسَائُه’ مِنَّ الْحُزْنِ مِثْلَ مَا اَضَاقَ نِسَائِيْ
In the name of Allah I'm not gonna leave him alone until,
I have his women taste the sorrow that my women have tasted.
He must be killed.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Take 50 camels from me now and 50 camels, when we return into Madina.
They refused, he offered them a second time.
Rasool Allah ﷺ kept on trying to solve this problem until, eventually they agreed and they accepted the blood money.
So, now the people of Muhallim(محلم),
they told Muhallim(محلم) go to Rasool Allah ﷺ
and tell him to ask for your forgiveness, to ask Allah to forgive you,
so Muhallim(محلم) came and he was already dressed in garments prepared for execution.
I mean he was prepared for death.
So, he came to Rasool Allah ﷺ and he was described as being a tall heavyset man.
He came to Rasool Allah ﷺ and sat down and said;
O Messenger of Allah, I am Muhallim(محلم) ask Allah to forgive me.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
اَللَّهُمَّ لَا تَغْفِرْلِيْ مُحَلِّم
O Allah do not forgive Muhallim(محلم).
He said: O Rasool Ullah, ask Allah to forgive me.
He ﷺ said it again.
اَللَّهُمَّ لَا تَغْفِرْلِيْ مُحَلِّم
O Allah do not forgive Muhallim(محلم).
The narrator of the Hadith(حديث) says, that
Muhallim(محلم) stood up covering his face to cover his tears.
And this is another lesson in the sanctity of the blood of a Muslim.
يَا أَيُّهَا الَّذِينَ آمَنُوا إِذَا ضَرَبْتُمْ فِي سَبِيلِ اللَّهِ فَتَبَيَّنُوا
فَتَبَيَّنُوا وَلَا تَقُولُوا لِمَنْ أَلْقَىٰ إِلَيْكُمُ السَّلَامَ لَسْتَ مُؤْمِنًا
تَبْتَغُونَ عَرَضَ الْحَيَاةِ الدُّنْيَا فَعِنْدَ اللَّهِ مَغَانِمُ كَثِيرَةٌ
كَذَٰلِكَ كُنْتُمْ مِنْ قَبْلُ فَمَنَّ اللَّهُ عَلَيْكُمْ فَتَبَيَّنُوا
إِنَّ اللَّهَ كَانَ بِمَا تَعْمَلُونَ خَبِيرًا۝
And Allahعَزّوجَلّ revealed the Ayah(آية), O you who have believed
when you go forth to fight in the cause of Allah, investigate
and do not say to one who gives you Salam(سلام)
you are not a believer aspiring for the goods, of worldly life
because Muhallim(محلم) he took over the camel of this man,
aspiring for the goods of worldly life.
For with Allah are many acquisitions.
You, yourself were like that before.
Meaning, there was a time when you were disbelievers.
Then Allah conferred his favour upon you, so investigate
indeed Allah is ever with, what you do acquainted.
Then there's another Sariyyah(سرية)
and this is the Sariyyah(سرية) of Abdullah Bin Hudaffa As-Sahmi رضي الله عنه.
Abdullah Bin Hudaffa(عبدالله بن حذافة) one of the Sahabah رضي الله عنه,
he was sent out in a Sariyyah(سرية).
The members of his Sariyyah(سرية) they did something that angered him.
So he was very upset, they had this fire, bonfire.
He told them, jump into it,
he told the members of his Sariyyah(سرية), to jump into the fire.
He said; I am the Ameer(أمير)
and you know that the Ta'ah(طاعة) of the Ameer(أمير) is Wajib(واجب) following the Ameer(أمير) is mandatory,
so jump into the fire.
They refused, the Sahabah(صحابه) refused, and then he calm down after that
and when they returned to Rasool Allah ﷺ and they asked him about the situation
what did Rasool Allah ﷺ say?. He said;
لَوْ دَخَلُوْهَا مَا خَرَجُوْا مِنْهَا اِنَّمَا الطَّاعَةْ فِيْ الْمَعْرُوْفَ
If they entered into that fire, they would never have left it because obedience is in good.
Rasool Allah ﷺ is saying, that if they jumped into that fire, they would have remained in Hellfire
because you should only obey the Ameer(أمير) when he instructs you to do good
but he if he orders you to do evil
then you do not follow him. And this Hadith(حديث) is Muttafiq Alaih(متفق عليه),
so the rule is,
لَا طَاعَة لْمَخْلُوْقِ فِيْ مَعْصِيَة الْخَالِقْ
We should not obey the creation, in disobeying the Creator.
As long as the Ameer(أمير) gives instructions that are Halal(حلال) and allowed then we follow.
As soon as they tell us to do something that is Haram(حرام) we refuse.
So, if the ruler orders that the women should take out their Hijab(حجاب)
then that order should be disobeyed
if the ruler orders Muslims to not fast in Ramadan(رمضان) because it affects productivity
then we must disobey
if the ruler bans Jihad(جهاد) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله)
than he should be disobeyed.
If the ruler wants the Muslims to be loyal to the Yahood(يهود) and the Christians
and to be disloyal towards the ones who are practicing the religion of Allah
he should be disobeyed
so the ruler is obeyed, when he instructs good
and he is disobeyed, when he's instructing evil.
Umra Tul Qadhaa(عُمرة الْقَضاء),
Rasool Allah ﷺ, the time has arrived to go and make Umrah(عمرة)
one year has passed since the signing of the treaty of Hudaybiyya(حديبية).
So, the Muslims, who were with him in Hudaybiyya(حديبية), joined him now to make Umrah(عمرة).
Rasool Allah ﷺ, the agreement that he had with Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), is that
he would only carry with him, the weapons of the traveler swords in their sheaths
but Rasool Allah ﷺ brought with him other weapons bows, arrows, spears
and when they reached close to Makkah.
The news was carried, that Rasool Allah ﷺ has brought arms other than the swords, so he must be preparing for war.
Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) said: We have done nothing wrong.
We did not break any of the agreements or the terms of the conditions of the agreement.
Why is Muhammadﷺ attacking us?
So, some of them went to Muhammadﷺ, and they told him;
يَا مُحَمَّدْمَا عُرِفْتَ صَغِيْرًا وَلَا كَبِيْرًابِالْغَدْرْ
تَدْخُلُ بِّالسلَاحِ عَلَى قَوْمِكَ فِيْ الْحَرَمْ وَقَدْ شَرَطَّت لَهُمْ اَن لَّا تَدْخُلَ اِلَّا بِسلَاحٍ مُسَافِرَ سُيُوْفِ قَرَّبْ
O Muhammad(محمد), you were not known, when you were young, or when you were old to betray,
you want to enter with weapons into Haram(حرم), against your people.
And you have given them the condition that
you will only enter with the weapons of the traveler, swords in their sheaths
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
اِنِّيْ لَا اَدْخُلُهَا بِالسلَاحٍ
I will not enter with these weapons.
Mickraz(مِكْرَزْ) said:
هَذَ الَّذِيْ تُعْرَفْ بِهْ، اَلْبِرُّ وَالْوَفَاءْ
This is what you are known to be a man of your word Birr(بِر) and Wafa'a(وفا) is good
and honesty and Wafa'a(وفا) is keeping one's word
So, over here, you can notice that, this was the reputation of Muhammadﷺ
and this is the Shahadah(شهادة) the witness of the Kuffar(كفار)
that he is a man of truth, and a man of his word.
And this is an important thing brothers and sisters to practice.
There's a Muslim character there are Muslim morals, there's a Muslim standard of conduct,
we should uphold these virtues in our dealings with Muslim and non Muslim
because we do it for the sake of Allah, and it is Ibadah(عبادة).
This is what the Kuffar(كفار) knew about Muhammadﷺ, that he was a man of truth
As-Sadiq(الصادق), Al-Ameen(ألأمين) the trustworthy and the truthful.
And in peace and war, the conduct of Rasool Allah ﷺ was the same
his character was that of a Muslim, the virtues of Islam, he was the living Qur'an(قرآن).
And it's important for us to live up to the standard of morals in Islam.
Rasool Allah ﷺ brought these weapons with him because he needed it as a protection, as a safeguard
but he was going to leave them outside of Makkah
and enter into Makkah only with his swords.
They entered into Makkah
and the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) they had, this hatred and this jealousy and animosity in their hearts,
they couldn't even stand being around the Muslims, so they vacated Makkah for three days
to allow Muhammadﷺ and the Muslims in there and they don't want to be with them
but they were on top of the mountains surrounding Makkah
and they were looking at the Muslims.
And they were saying among themselves that now the Muslims are going to come
and they are going to be weak, feeble because of the fever of Madina.
You remember we talked about the Madina was famous of this is endemic diseases that existed in there.
So the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) were saying that,
يَدْخُلْ عَلَيْنَا مُحَمَّدْ وَالْمُسْلِمُوْنْ وَ قَدْ وَهَنَتْهُمْ حمى يَثْرِبْ
The fever of Madina has made them weak.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ cared about the reputation of Muslims
and he wanted to give an image of strength
so he told the Muslims;
to uncover their right shoulder
and not to walk around Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه) as was the custom
but to do what is called the Ramel(رَمَلْ).
Ramel(رَمَلْ) is walking fast with strength it's like marching.
So, the Muslims would do that.
But between Rukn-e-Yamani(ركن أليماني) and Hijr-e-Aswad(حجر ألأسود)
because they would be concealed from the kuffar(كفار), the Kuffar(كفار) cannot see them
they would walk normally.
So, now brothers and sisters, if you go to Umrah(عمرة) or Al-Hajj(حَجْ),
you would notice that the Sunnah(سنة) is that
in the first three rounds, you would walk very fast, in this what's called the Ramel(رَمَلْ) it's like marching
but between Hijr-e-Aswad(حجر ألأسود) and Rukn-e-Yamani(ركن أليماني) you would walk normally.
Why?
because that was the area where the Ka'aba(كعبه) was covered the Muslims from the eyes of the Kuffar(كفار).
Rasool Allah ﷺ did not want to exhaust the Muslims.
But in the same time,
he didn't want the Kuffar(كفار) to take the impression that the Muslims are weak
so he had them do this Ramel(رَمَلْ), around three corners or three sides of Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه)
while the forth side they would walk
and if it wasn't for the fact that it was truly exhaust the Muslims
he would have, had them do it for the seven rounds.
Even though this was done with that objective
but the Sunnah(سنة) remained and we still do it, until this day.
Rasool Allah ﷺ sent one of the Sahabah(صحابه) to do the engagement
he wanted to get married to Maimoonah Bint Al-Haris(ميمونه بنت ألحارث).
Maimoonah(ميمونة), she agreed, and she said: My Wali(ولي), to sign the contract would be Al-Abbas(العباس).
Al-Abbas(العباس) was married to her sister Umm Ul-Fazal(أم الفضل)
and Rasool Allah ﷺ wanted to hold the Walimah(وليمه) in Makkah
but the three days were over.
So Huwaitib Ibn Abdul Uzza(حويطب إبن عبدالعزى) he came to Rasool Allah ﷺ and said;
اُنَاشِدَكَ الله وَالْعهدَ الَذِيْ بَيْنَنَا
I ask you in the name of Allah and the contract between us to leave.
I mean, they have this hatred to Rasool Allah ﷺ and they couldn't stand the Muslims
and they were waiting for the three days to finish
and they immediately, came asking the Muslims to leave.
Rasool Allah ﷺ told them;
I have married a woman from among you
it won't harm you if I finished my wedding to her
and we prepare a feast and you can join us.
You're welcome to come, and join this Walima(وليمه).
They said: We ask you in the name of Allah to leave.
Now, when they came to him, Rasool Allah ﷺ was sitting with some of Al-Ansaar(الأنْصَار)
Saad Ibn Ubadah(سعدابن عبادة) and other Ansaar(أنْصَار).
And they said; We want you to leave from our land.
So, Saad Ibn Ubadah(سعدابن عبادة) angrily responded back and said;
This is not your land or the land of your fathers.
Rasool Allah ﷺ calmed him down and said: We would leave, and they left.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ held whatever remained from the celebration of his wedding,
he held it outside of Makkah in a place called Sarf(سرف)
and Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله),
Maimoonah(ميمونة) later on would end up dying in the same place where she married Rasool Allah ﷺ.
When Rasool Allah ﷺ was leaving from Makkah, the daughter of Hamza(حمزه), young girl
she came running saying Ya Amm(يا عَمّْ), Ya Amm(يا عَمّْ), Ya Amm(يا عَمّْ), Ya Amm(يا عَمّْ).
O Uncle, O Uncle, O Uncle.
So, Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) grabbed her
and handed her over to Fatima(فاطمه) and said take care of your cousin, to take her back to Madina
Jafar(جعفر) said: No, I'm going to take her.
Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) said: I am her cousin,
Jafar(جعفر) said: I'm her cousin too,
and then Zaid(زيد) came in and said; She is the daughter of my uncle.
So, what happened was Rasool Allah ﷺ came in, to judge between them.
Because of this conflict the voices were..... Ya'ani(يعني) they had a conflict among them
who will take care of the daughter of Hamza رضي الله عنه.
So, Rasool Ullah came to judge between them and he handed her over to Jafar(جعفر)
because Jafar(جعفر) was married to her Aunt, to the Aunt of the daughter of Hamza(حمزه).
Zaid(زيد) Actually he said: She's the daughter of my uncle
because Zaid(زيد) was the adopted son of Muhammadﷺ and
Hamza(حمزه) is the Uncle of Rasool Allah ﷺ
but also Hamza(حمزه) is the brother of Rasool Allah ﷺ because of breastfeeding.
The same woman breastfed, both Muhammadﷺ and Hamza(حمزه)
so Hamza(حمزه) is the uncle of Rasool Ullah and his brother in Radha'a(رضَاعى) too.
So, that makes the daughter of Hamza(حمزه) the Cousin of Zaid(زيد),
Rasool Allah ﷺ handed her over to Jafar(جعفر) and then Rasool Allah ﷺ told Ali(علي)
اَنْتَ مِنِّيْ وَ اَنَا مِنْكْ
You are from me, and I am from you.
And he told Jafar Ibn Abi Talib رضي الله عنه
اَشْبَهْتَ خَلْقِيْ وَخُلُقِيْ
You are our similar to me in manners and in looks,
and he told Zaid Ibn Harissa رضي الله عنه.
اَنْتَ اَخُوْنَا وَ مَوْلَانَا
You are our brother and our companion.
And then Ali Bin Abi Talib رضي الله عنه he told Rasool Allah ﷺ
wouldn't you marry Hamza(حمزه)'s daughter.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ said: She is the daughter of my brother from breastfeeding, Al-Bukhari(ألبخاري),
which makes her Mahrum(محرم) for him, he cannot therefore marry her.
We are done with the events of the seventh year of Hijrah(هجرة).
Now, we move on to the events of the eighth year of Hijrah(هجرة) and this is a very busy year.
We have the Islam of Khalid(خالد), Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) and Uthman Ibn Talha(عُثمان ابن طلحه)
then we have the battle of Mao'ta(مؤته).
The first proper battle between the Muslims and Roman Empire,
and then there's Fattah Makkah(فتح مكه) and the great battle of Hunain(حنين)
and the siege of At-Taef(اَلطَّائِف).
So, it's a very busy year.
We'll start with the story of the Islam of Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) and Khalid(خالد).
Amr Bin Aas رضي الله عنه said: I fought against Rasool Allah ﷺ in the Battle of Badr(بدر)
and Allah saved me.
And then I fought against Muhammadﷺ in the Battle of Uhud(أحَد)
and Allah saved me,
then I fought against Muhammadﷺ in the Battle of Khandaq(خندق)
and Allah saved me.
Now when is Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) speaking, saying this.
He's saying this after I became Muslim.
So, now he's looking back at his memories.
And he's thinking about him and saying, Man, I was, I was fighting the Messenger of Allah,
what in the world was I doing?
I mean, then being a Mushrik(مشرك), being a disbeliever,
the way he would think about things is different.
And now when he looks back at it, and say wait a minute,
I was fighting against the Messenger of Allah.
And these are the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم,
who loved Rasool Allah ﷺ, more than anything in the world.
So, after every battle, he would say, and Allah saved me, meaning if I died then,
I would have been in hellfire.
So, he's going through his history. He said;
I fought against Rasool Allah ﷺ in Badr(بدر), and then I fought against him in Uhud(أحَد)
and then I fought against him in Al-Khandaq(الخندق)
and I was beginning to feel that, no matter what Muhammad(محمد) is gonna win!
His armies are getting better and better, his Da'wah(دعوة) is spreading more and more
and we are getting more constricted and narrowed in our movement day after day.
So, Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) was starting to feel this conflict and depression
that a Kafir(كافر) would have when he sees the victory of Islam.
I mean there's so much built up envy, jealousy, hatred that builds up in the hearts of the Kuffar(كفار).
I mean, you have to keep in mind that
Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ) is the one who's dominating the heart of the disbeliever,
so all of these feelings are bottled up inside the heart of Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص)
so he just had enough of it and he decided that he's going to leave Makkah
and go and stay in a place called Al-Wahat(ألْوَحَتْ) .
he took his family, he took his wealth and he went there and he said;
وَاَقْلَلْتُ مِنَّ النَّاسْ
And I stayed away from people.
He just want to stay away from everyone,
and then, when the contract of Al-Hudaybiyya(ألْحُدَيْبِيه) occurred,
when Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) were forced to admit the existence of the Islamic State
and they were forced to admit the authority of Muhammadﷺ.
I mean when some of the Sahabah(صحابه) complained about Uhud(أحَد),
Rasool Allah ﷺ reminded them about the days of Uhud(أحَد), the early days of Islam and he told them;
Now Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) have accepted peace from you.
He was turning their attention to the great developments that were occurring
and we said that Hudaybiyya(ألْحُدَيْبِيه) was a great victory for Islam.
So, Al-Hudaybiyya(ألْحُدَيْبِيه) when it happened, Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص),
he said tomorrow Muhammad(محمد) will enter into Makkah, it's inevitable.
Muhammadﷺ is going to come in,
it reached to the degree that Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) have been unable to fight him, when he's at the doorsteps of Makkah,
and they accepted to sign a treaty with him,
this is a sign of the fact that sooner or later Muhammadﷺ will enter into Makkah.
So, he ruled out staying in Makkah, and he ruled out staying in At-Taef(اَلطَّائِف)
and these are the two major cities of Al-Hijaaz(ألحجاز),
he called some of the members of his clan.
And Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) was a man who was respected among his people
and they used to listen to him, and they see to him as being their guide.
So, he called these people who had trust in him, and he told them;
اِنِّيْ اَرى اَمْرَ محمد يَعُّلُو الْاُمُوْرَا كُلَّهَا، عُلُّوًا مُنْكَرَا
I can see that the affair of Muhammad(محمد) is rising above all others in a horrible way.
I mean, he's seeing the events unfolding in front of his eyes.
And through his wisdom and intelligence, he can read through these events in history
and see that Muhammadﷺ and Islam are slowly but surely rising, and rising, and rising against everything else.
I can see this with my own eyes.
And he's a disbeliever, but he can sense and feel that, he can see it,
just like some of the Kuffar(كفار) today can see it.
While unfortunately many of the Muslims are failing to see it
and they are deep in their sleep, and they cannot see
what is happening and unfolding of the events, the Ummah(امة) today,
and they are failing to see the victory of Allahعَزّوجَلّ  that is on its way.
So, Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص), told his people;
Therefore, I don't think it's a good idea for us to stay in Makkah.
Rather, I believe that we should go and stay with An-Najashi(النجاشي), in Abyssinia.
Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) had a good relationship with An-Najjashi(ألنجاشي).
So, he wanted to put that into use and he said, let's go and stay over there.
If Muhammadﷺ is victorious, then we are away from him.
And if he loses and Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) wins
then Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), they already know who we are, and what our position is.
And Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) said about himself,
and I would see that if all Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) became Muslim, I would never become Muslim.
I mean, that's how much hatred he had in his heart to Islam.
If all of my people, every single one of them in Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) becomes Muslim, I'm not.
So, they agreed with his assessment and opinion
and they decided to travel together and go to Abyssinia, to leave their land, to make Hijrah(هجرة).
What is the driving force behind that, it is Hatred towards Islam.
He said; Let's take gifts for An-Najashi(النجاشي),
and the thing that An-Najashi(النجاشي) loved most was Hide, leather.
So, his people gathered all what they could from the best hide they could find.
And they took a boat and went to An-Najashi(النجاشي), in Abyssinia.
They went to visit An-Najashi(النجاشي).
And who did they find coming out from the court of An-Najashi(النجاشي), Amr Bin Umayyah Ad-Dhamri(عمرو بن أمَيَّة اَلضَمْرِي),
who was sent by Rasool Allah ﷺ to perform the marriage of Rasool Allah ﷺ to the daughter of Abu Sufiyan(ابو سفيان), Umm Habiba(ام حبيبه)
and also to call the Muhajireen(مهاجرين) of Abyssinia to go back to Madina.
So, Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص), saw him coming out from the court of An-Najashi(النجاشي), the Palace of An-Najashi(النجاشي).
Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) entered, obviously he entered alone, the rest of his companions had to wait for him.
And he went and made Sajood(سجود) to the king, as was the tradition
and he was very well received.
An-Najashi(النجاشي) told them;
Welcome my friend, have you brought me any gifts from your land.
He said: Yes, I did.
King O King, I have brought you some Hide.
And then he presented the king with the pieces of Hide that he has brought
the king was very happy and pleased with it.
And right then and there he distributed some of it to his patriarchs,
and then the rest he ordered that it would be registered and recorded,
and then deposited and kept in a safe place.
And then Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص), he got carried away
he saw how well the reception was, and how happy the king was with the gift.
So, he told the king: O King, I have seen a man come out from your palace
who is the Messenger of our enemy, the man who has killed the noble among us,
would you hand him over to me, so that we could kill him.
An-Najashi(النجاشي) immediately hit Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) in the face
and Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) said: I thought that my nose was broken,
and blood started flowing out of my nostrils, and I was covering it with my clothes,
and I wish that the Earth would swallow me
because of the embarrassment I felt and the fear I felt from the king.
And then Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) said;
If I knew, O King if I knew that you dislike what I said, I wouldn't have said it.
And then the king said, An-Najashi(النجاشي) said;
يَا عمْرو تَسْألُنِيْ
You are asking me O Amr(عمرو), to hand you over
the Messenger of the man who receives An-Namoos Al-Akbar(أناموس ألأكبر),
and An-Namoos Al-Akbar(ألناموس ألأكبر) is Jibreel عليه السّلام.
O Amr(عمرو) you're asking me,
to hand over to you the messenger of the man who receives An-Namoos Al-Akbar(ألناموس ألأكبر),
so that you may kill him.
Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) said: Right then and there I had a change of heart,
and I told myself: The Arabs and the non Arabs recognize the truth and I do not.
And that is when my heart changed.
Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله),
look at how Allahسُبْحَانه وتعالى guided Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص).
He lived with Rasool Allah ﷺ Thirteen(13) years in Makkah
and he knew him, very well and he did not become Muslim then
and he becomes a Muslim in the court of An-Najashi(النجاشي) in a foreign land,
in that particular moment, Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) said I told An-Najashi(النجاشي).
اَتَشْهَدْ بِذَالِكْ
Is that you witnesses, is that your testimony?
An-Najashi(النجاشي) said;
نَعَمْ اَشْهَدُ عِنْدَاللهِ بِهْ
I testify with that in front of Allah
and then he said;
يَا عمْرو، اَطَّعْنِيْ وَاتببِعْ
فَوَلله اِنَّهْ لَعَلَى الْحَقْ
وَلَيَظْهَرَنَّ عَلَى مَنْ خَالَفَه’ كَمَا ظَهَرَ مُوْسَى عَلَى فِرْعَوْنَ وَجُنُوْدِهْ
O Amr(عمرو), listen to me and follow him
because in the name of Allah, he is on truth and he will prevail against all of his enemies.
Just like Musa(موسى) prevailed against Firoun(فرعون) and his soldiers.
An-Najashi(النجاشي) in this faraway land, this is his testimony about Rasool Allah ﷺ.
An-Najashi(النجاشي) was a man of truth, he was a man who understood religion,
he was a man who understood history,
he was a man who understood the lives of the prophets,
and he is giving Da'wah(دعوة) to Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص).
Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) who knows Rasool Allah ﷺ,
knows about Islam and knows about the Muslims is receiving Da'wah(دعوة) from An-Najashi(النجاشي).
You know the way Da'wah(دعوة) works, it defies all logic,
therefore we should not have any fixed beliefs about it,
and you can see throughout the Da'wah(دعوة) of Rasool Allah ﷺ, amazing things,
Abu Talib(ابوطالب) does not become Muslim,
while you have Abu Dhar Al-Ghaffari(أبوذرألغفاري) becoming Muslim.
Abu Lahab(أبولهب) the uncle of Rasool Allah ﷺ does not become Muslim
and Salman Al-Farisi(سلمان ألفارسي) comes all the way from Persia and becomes Muslim,
it defies all rules.
Hidaya(هدايه), guidance is something that belongs to Allah.
إِنَّكَ لَا تَهْدِي مَنْ أَحْبَبْتَ وَلَٰكِنَّ اللَّهَ يَهْدِي مَنْ يَشَاءُ ۚ
You do not guide those whom you want, it is Allah, Who guides whom He wills.
Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) said: At that moment, I gave him baiyah(بيعة) to become Muslim.
And An-Najashi(النجاشي) took my pledge to follow and Obey Rasool Allah ﷺ and become Muslim.
Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله), Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) came with an intention and is coming back with another intention,
he came for an objective and now he's coming a completely different human being.
Subhan Allah(سُبْحَان الله)
وَمَا يَعْلَمُ جُنُودَ رَبِّكَ إِلَّا هُوَ ۚ
Nobody knows about the soldiers of Allah but He.
An-Najashi(النجاشي) was a soldier of Allah
and through him, Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) this great man(becomes Muslim)
and you can read the history of Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) and see what Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) did for Islam.
His Da'wah(دعوة), his acceptance of Islam came through An-Najashi(النجاشي)
and he was such a great enemy of a Islam and now he becomes a Muslim.
An-Najashi(النجاشي) then ordered some new clothes to be brought for me
because of my clothes were soaked in blood.
And then I came out and when my companion saw me wearing some new clothes,
they were quite happy, and they felt that things were going well.
Before I went in I told them,
that I'm going to try to convince An-Najashi(النجاشي) to hand me over Amr Bin Umayyah Ad-Dhamri(عمرو بن أمَيَّة اَلضَمْرِي),
so that I could kill him.
And this would gain a good reputation for us with Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
So, now they asked him, What did he do?
He said, Well, I didn't feel that was good to propose this to him in our first meeting, but I will do that next time.
They said: That's a good idea.
Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) said: I said I'm going to go for some business I have
and he didn't tell him what his plans were, Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) left.
He took a boat and went towards Madina, he just left them without a word.
These men who, he brought out with intention of fleeing away from Muhammadﷺ.
As soon as he reaches, he leaves them in Abyssinia and goes to Muhammadﷺ.
You know, Hidaya(هدايه) is a strange thing.
So, Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) reached to a place called Sha'aibah(شُعَيْبَه)
and then he goes and reaches Marr Az-Zahraan(مَرَّ ألظَهْرَان),
when he gets to this place called Marr Az-Zahraan(مَرَّ ألظَهْرَان)
and he's traveling towards the Madina, he sees two men,
one of them was in a tent and the other one was tying the camels.
Who were these two men?
Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) and Uthman Ibn Talha(عثمان إبن طلحه),
he walked up to them and said;
What are you doing?
Where are you going?
Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) said: There's no one left, no one worthy left
and Muhammadﷺ, he is prevailing, so we want to go and become Muslim.
Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) said: This is the same reason that brought me
and I see this also at the striking thing
that, these men who were, say among the leaders of the effort to fight the Islam Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) and Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد)
and Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) he belongs to the family of Bannu Makhzoom(بنو مخزوم) who were enemies of Islam,
his father many Ayaat(آيات) were revealed about his father
and then also Abu Jahal(ابوجَهَل) belongs to the same family
and then you have Uthman Ibn Talha(عثمان إبن طلحه).
Uthman Ibn Talha(عثمان إبن طلحه) belongs to Bannu Abd-Ad-Daar(بنوعبد ألدار)
very noble family in Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), they were the ones, who carry the banner in war,
and they're the ones who hold the key of Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه)
and by the way, they still hold, until this day,
the key is inherited from father to son all the way until this day.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ said: The key should remain among you until the Day of Judgment,
no one shall take it from you but a transgressor.
So, these three men belong to these prominent families in Quraish(قُرَيْشْ)
and they're very important figures
and Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله)
they all meet together, I mean what a coincidence
and nothing is a coincidence, everything happens through the Qadar(قَدَر) of Allahعَزّوجَلّ, it's preordained.
Now, we're talking about 20 years fighting Islam
and they meet along the path to Madina,
so that they would travel and enter Madina together, the three of them.
They reach to the outskirts of Madina
and they hear somebody say;
يا رباح ،يا رباح، يا رباح
Rabbah(رباح) the derivative of Rabbah(رباح) is Ribh(رِبْحْ) and that means profit,
something that you gain.
So, Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) said: We took it as a good omen,
and then someone saw us and said;
قَدْ اَلْقتْ مَكَّهْ اِلَيْكُمْ مَقَالِيْدَ هَا بَعْدَهَذَيْنْ
Makkah has handed over its reins to you after these two men
and he was referring to Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) and Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد)
meaning that who is left in Makkah, after Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) and Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) become Muslim.
It is as if Makkah has handed over its reins to Rasool Allah ﷺ after these men became Muslim.
Because as I said, you know
these men they constitute the second generation of leadership that was fighting Islam,
I mean you have the first generation and these are Abu Jahal(ابوجَهَل), Abu Lahab(ابولهب), Umayyah Bin Khalaf(أمَيَّة بن خلف),
Ubaye Bin Khalaf(أبَي بن خلف), Abu Sufiyan(ابو سفيان), Al-Waleed Bin Mugheera(ألْوَلِيد بن مُغِيرَة)
these were the prominent personalities, who're leading the effort to fight Islam,
in the early days up to the Battle of Badr(بدر).
The Battle of Badr(بدر) was the day in which the forces of evil were crushed
and the entire first generation of leadership was exterminated,
the only one that remained from those men was Abu Sufiyan(ابوسفيان).
He is the only man who survived
and the reason he survived is because he didn't attend Badr(بدر).
Because the whole reason why Badr(بدر) occurred was to protect his caravan that he was leading.
Utba Bin Rabiyah(عُتْبَة بن ربيعة), Shaybah(شَيْبَة), Al-Waleed(وَليد), Abu Jahal(ابوجَهَل),
Umayyah Bin Khalaf(أمَيَّة بن خلف), Ubaye Bin Khalaf(أبَي بن خلف), they were all killed.
And some of them already died before that like a Abu Lahab(ابولهب).
And I mean, he didn't die in the Battle of Badr(بدر), he died in Makkah.
So the next generation that took over leadership
where people like Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد), Ikrimah Bin Abi Jahal(عكْرِمَة بن أبي جهل)
and Sufwaan Ibn Umayyah(صَفْوَان ابن أمَيَّة), Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص).
So they represented the new blood, the new leadership in Makkah,
for these men to become Muslim was such a devastating blow, to the people of Makkah
and that's why this man saw it as if Makkah has lost it, and that's it,
they're handing over the reins of leadership to Rasool Allah ﷺ, after the Islam of these men.
They came into Madina and Rasool Allah ﷺ was eagerly waiting for them
smiling all the time while they're walking towards him,
they can see this beaming smile on the face of Rasool Allah ﷺ, he was so happy for their Islam
and this is the true Da'wah(دعوة),
and Rasool Allah ﷺ didn't have anything against them even though they are fought against him in Battlefield,
they've spoken against him, they have harmed him, they have driven him out of his land
but Rasool Allah ﷺ was looking at the interest of Islam.
And was happy because these men are now going to become soldiers of Allah.
Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) said;
I told Rasool Allah ﷺ, O Rasool Ullah I pledge my allegiance to you
with the condition that Allah forgives for me all my past sins.
He said: I forgot to ask Him to forgive them for me, my forthcoming sins.
Rasool Allah ﷺ told me;
يَا عمْرو، اَمَا تَعْلَمْ اَنَّ الْاِسْلَامَ يَجُّبُ مَا قَبْلَهَا
وَاَنَّ الْهِجْرَۃ تَجُبُّ مَا قَبْلَهَا
وَ اَنَّ الْحَجَّ يَجُبُّ مَا قَبْلَهَا
O Amr(عمرو), don't you know that Islam erases everything before it,
and that Hijrah(هجرة) erases everything before it
and that Hajj(حَجْ) erases everything before it.
So, these 3 deeds, they erase everything.
So, you can see how important Hajj(حَجْ) and Hijrah(هجرة) are,
Rasool Allah ﷺ equated them to Islam, that they erase everything that occurs before.
Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) said; Rasool Allah ﷺ took a lot of care of us
and he used to put us ahead of many of the companions
and that remained to be the case until he passed away.
And then the same thing with Abu Bakr(ابوبكر), he took a lot of care of me and Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد)
and then in the time of Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب),
he used to give a lot of attention to me and appoint me in important positions of responsibility.
However, the relationship between Umar(عُمَر) and Khalid(خالد) as he says,
كَانَ كَالْعَاتِبْ عَلَى خَالِد
He was disapproving of some of the actions of Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد).
So, this is the story accordingly to the narration of Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص).
We'll see what Khalid Ibn Waleed رضي الله عنه said, Khalid(خالد) said;
قَدْ شَهِدْ تَّ هَذِهِ الْمَوَاطِنْ كُلَّهَا عَلَى محمدٍ صلى الله عليه وسلم فَلَيْسَ فِيْ مَوْطِنْ اَشْهَدُه’ اِلَّا اَنْصَرِفْ
وَاَنَا اَرَى فِيْ نَفْسِيْ اَنِّيْ مُوْضِعٌ فِيْ غَيْرِ شَيْء وَ اَنَّ مُحمَّدً سَيَظْهَرْ
He said: I have attended all of these battles against Muhammad(محمد),
and in every situation I attend, I leave with this feeling in my heart
that I'm putting my effort in something that is wasted
and that in the end, Muhammad(محمد) will prevail.
So, we had this deep feeling in his heart that what he's doing is wrong,
there is something wrong with it, and that this man will be victorious and will prevail
he said until, Hudaybiyya(ألحديبية) came,
he said; I lead a contingent of Kuffar(كفار) two hundred men
and Rasool Allah ﷺ and the Muslims were praying Salaat-uz-Zohar(صلاة الظهر),
he said: I was face to face I met Muhammadﷺ face to face while they were praying
and that was my opportunity to attack them in Salah(صلاة).
But I was reluctant to do so.
Now, this word coming from Khalid Ibn Waleed رضي الله عنه is strange
because he was the furthest from being a reluctant person
he was a very decisive man.
So, for Khalid(خالد) to say that I was reluctant to attack him, and he said, and that was good,
Allah saved him
and he was reluctant at that moment
because Allahعَزّوجَلّ wanted something good for Khalid Ibn Waleed رضي الله عنه.
He said: So Salah(صلاة) finished I didn't take that opportunity,
so I decided that I'm going to attack them, in Salaat-Ul-Asr(صلاة العصر)
he said: By the time they came to pray Asr(عصر),
Rasool Allah ﷺ was already praying Salaat-Ul-Khaof(صلاةالخوف).
Salah(صلاة) where half of the army prays and half of them protects the rest.
فَعَلِمْتُ اَنَّ الرَّجُلَ مَمْنُوْعَ
I knew that this man is being protected.
So, Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) carries on with the narration and says;
When Rasool Allah ﷺ came the following year to do Umra-Tul-Qadhaa(عُمْرَةُالْقَضَاء),
when Rasool Allah ﷺ came to do Umra-Tul-Qadhaa(عُمْرَةُالْقَضَاء),
his brother, Al-Waleed Bin Waleed(ألوليد بن وليد) came looking for him.
Now, Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) was among the Kuffar(كفار) who vacated Makkah for the Muslims
because they didn't want to see them, they just left.
So, Al-Waleed(ألوليد) came looking for his brother, Khalid(خالد),
and when he didn't find him, he left him a letter.
What did he say? He said;
بِسْمِ الله الرَحْمن الرَّحِيْمْ۝
اَمَّا بَعْدْ
فَاِنِّيْ لَمْ اَرَى اَعْجَبْ
مِنْ ذَهَابَ رَاْيِكَ عَنِ الْاِسْلَامْ
وَعَقْلُكْ وَعَقْلُكْ
وَ مِثْلُ الْاِسْلَامِ ما جَهلَه’ اَحَدْ؟
وَقَدْ سَاَلَنِيْ رَسُول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم عَنْكَ، وَقَالَ: اَيْنَ خَالِدْ؟
فَقُلتَ: يَاْتِيْ بِهِ الله
. فَقَالَ: " مَا مِثْلُه’ جَهِلَ الْاِسْلَامْ
وَلَوْ كَانَ جَعَلَ نِكَايَتَه’ وَحْدَه’ مَعَ الْمُسْلِمِيْنَ كَانَ خَيْرَا لَّهْ
وَلَقَدَّمْنَاه’ عَلَى غَيْرِهْ"، فَا سْتَدْرِكْ يَا اَخِيْ مَا فَاتَكْ، فَقَدْ فَاتَكَ مَوَاطِنْ صَالِحة
He said;
بِسْمِ الله الرَحْمن الرَّحِيْمْ۝
In the name of Allah the Most Merciful and Most compassionate.
I know of nothing more strange then your antipathy for Islam
being as intelligent as you are.
Could anyone disregard something like Islam.?
Rasool Allah ﷺ has asked me about you, he said; Where is Khalid(خالد),
I replied, Allah will bring him.
He then asked; Could someone like him disregard Islam.
If he were to put his energy and bravery to work with the Muslims, it would be better for him.
We would certainly give him precedents before others.
Take note brother of what good things you are missing.
Rasool Allah ﷺ is asking about Khalid(خالد), where is Khalid(خالد)?
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ is sending Khalid(خالد) a message through his brother.
He's telling him that it's not appropriate for someone like you
as intelligent as you are, to stay away from Islam
and if you become Muslim we'll put you ahead of many others.
This is true Da'wah(دعوة), dear brothers and sisters.
The fact that Rasool Allah ﷺ was asking about him, cares about him
because Khalid(خالد) said;
The question of Rasool Allah ﷺ, when Rasool Allah ﷺ asked about me, that affected me a lot.
And this is what made Khalid(خالد) decide, to make his move and become Muslim.
It is the fact that Rasool Allah ﷺ had him on his mind
it is the fact that Rasool Allah ﷺ thought about him, gave him a thought,
and to admit that even though he's a Kafir(كافر).
But to say that he's an intelligent man, how could his mind not understand and recognize Islam
and then also the fact, that Rasool Allah ﷺ said: We'll put him ahead of many others.
The status in Islam is according to how early you become Muslim.
I mean, that was the status that the Sahabah(صحابه) held
you have the, the earlier Sahabi(صحابي) becomes Muslim, the higher he is held,
and that is only reasonable because As-sabq(ألسبق) being ahead, shows a state of heart with the person
but here Rasool Allah ﷺ was saying even though Khalid(خالد) may become Muslim late,
but we will put them ahead of many others. Why?
Because of the consideration that Rasool Allah ﷺ had for the status of Khalid(خالد),
his intelligence, his abilities
and this is an important thing for the leader and the Daaiyaah(داعية),
to recognize the abilities of people, people are not the same, they are different.
Some people have qualities that others don't possess
some people have specialties that others don't possess,
some people are strong, some people are weak, some people are intelligent,
some people are less intelligent, you know people are different.
Allah سبحانه وتعالى has divided this Rizq(رزق) among people
and everybody has a different capability
and leadership is the ability to put the right person in the right place.
Khalid Bin Waleed رضي الله عنه decided that he's going to leave and he's going to become Muslim.
And he had a dream he saw himself in a very narrow constricted place
and that's he's walking out of this place into a very vast and beautiful area.
When he asked for the interpretation of the dream later on,
Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) told him; It means that, this is you leaving Shirk(شرك) and entering into Islam.
He went to Safwaan(صفوان),
so he wanted to talk to his close friends, Safwaan Ibn Umayyah(صفوان ابن أمية) being one of them.
He went to Safwaan(صفوان) and told him that I want to become Muslim you like to join me.?
Safwaan(صفوان) said; If no one but me remains I'm not gonna become Muslim.
So, Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) said: Well this is the man whose father and brother were killed by the Muslims.
So, then he went to Ikrimah Bin Abi Jahal(عكرمة بن أبي جهل) he told him;
That our situation is, with the Muslims, with Muhammad(محمد) is like a fox in a hole.
You drop bucket of water over him and he's going to come out running.
In other words, Muhammadﷺ is surrounding us
and we are like fox in a hole and all what Muhammadﷺ and the Muslims have to do is to thou us with a bucket of water,
and we're going to come out running. We have nothing left.
So, what do you think about becoming Muslim. Ikrimah(عكرمة), refused,
so Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) told him well, don't tell anybody about it.
And then Khalid(خالد), he met Uthman Bin Talha(عثمان ابن طلحه), and said how about I talked to him?
And then he said: No, I'm not gonna talk to him because he lost his family in Uhud(أحَد).
I mean, seven family members of Uthman Bin Talha(عثمان ابن طلحه) were killed under the banner of the Mushrikeen(مشركين).
So, he said: I'm not going to speak to him.
And then he said, Well, what difference that it's make, I'm leaving anyway.
So, let me just talk to him.
And he went to Uthman(عثمان) and proposed the idea to him, and
Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله) he found him to be very receptive and he agreed to go immediately.
And this tells us that we shouldn't have pre judgments about people
and again, we go back to the issue of Hidayah(هداية)
we don't know, who's going to be guided and who won't and we should not rule out anything,
and you should never close the gates of hope for anyone
and this is a man who Khalid(خالد) thought in the beginning that he won't be receptive
and then Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله) he found him to be the most receptive among the three.
Even though, he is the one who lost seven of his family members in the Battle of Uhud(أحَد).
So, never give up on anyone we spread out the message, our responsibility is to give Balaagh(بلاغ)
and then it is Allah(الله), who guides, we're not responsible for the results.
We have to do our part we do it as an Ibadah(عبادة) for Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
But it is Allah who controls the hearts of men.
Khalid(خالد) told Uthman(عثمان), we meet in this particular place
if you arrive before me you wait, until I come,
if I arrived there before you I wait for you, until you come.
They travelled and then they met with Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص)
we already talked about that and when they reached to the outskirts of Madina,
Khalid(خالد) said: We stopped and then we changed our clothes and we put our best clothes on.
This is how they wanted to meet Rasool Allah ﷺ.
They were dressed up in their best clothes to go and meet Rasool Allah ﷺ,
preparing themselves for this, for the greatest moment, in their lives.
And when Khalid(خالد) met Rasool Allah ﷺ,
Rasool Ullah told him come here after he gave his pledge,
and then Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
اَلْحَمدُلله، اَلَّذِيْ هَدَاكْ
قَدْ كُنْتُ اَرَى لَكَ  عَقْلًا رَجَوْت اَنْ لَّا يُسْلِمَكَ اِلَّا اِلَى خَيْرْ
Al-Hamdolillah(ألْحمدلله), Praise be to Allah, who guided you.
I used to see that you are intelligent
and I hope that your intelligence would only bring you, or only guide you towards good.
Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) said;
That Rasool Allah ﷺ put me ahead of many of his companions and took a lot of care of me.
And we would see the manifestation of that in the rest of Seerah(سيرة).
Rasool Allah ﷺ appointed an army of 3000 strong
to attack the lands of the Romans in Ash-sham(ألشام).
And this was to be the first encounter between the Muslims and the Romans
and also the first encounter between Muslims and Christians.
There was something unique this time in the appointment of the Umara'a(أمرآء), on this army, the leaders of this army,
usually the cases that Rasool Allah ﷺ would appoint one Ameer(أمير) for the army and that's it.
This time it was different,
Rasool Allah ﷺ said that the Ameer(أمير) is Zaid Ibn Harissa(زيد بن حارثه)
فَاِنْ اُصِيْبْ
If he is killed, then Jafar Ibn Abi Talib(جعفر إبن أبي طالب)
If he is killed, then Abdullah Bin Rawaha(عبدالله بن رواحة).
So, Allah-O-Alam(الله اعلم) it could be that the risk and the danger of this encounter,
demanded that Rasool Allah ﷺ take the additional step of appointing two Umara'a(أمرآء) as backup for the first
or it could be because Rasool Allah ﷺ knew beforehand
that they would be killed Allah-O-Alam(الله اعلم).
But we don't find anywhere else in the Seerah(سيرة) of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
that Rasool Allah ﷺ appointed backup Umara'a(أمرآء), in case the first is killed.
So this is something unique with what we refer to as Ghazwat Maota(غزوة المؤته).
There's something else that is unique with Ghazwat Maota(غزوة المؤته), this is the only time in Seerah(سيرة)
where an army that is not led by Rasool Allah ﷺ is called Ghazwa(غزوة).
Usually a Ghazwa(غزوة) is an army in which Rasool Allah ﷺ participates
and a Sariyyah(سرية) is an army in which Rasool Allah ﷺ does not participate
that is how it is in the books of Seerah(سيرة).
So, whenever you see Ghazwa(غزوة) you know that Rasool Allah ﷺ was there
and whenever you see the title Sariyyah(سرية), dispatch you know that Rasool Allah ﷺ was not there.
With Maota(مؤته), it is called Ghazwa(غزوة) and all the books of Seerah(سيرة),
I mean that's what Al-Bukhari(ألبخاري) calls it, that's what Ibn Hishaam(إبن هشام) calls it
Ibn Is'haqq(اِبْنِ اِسْحَاقْ), Al-Waqadie(ألواقدي)
they all agree on calling this a as Ghazwa(غزوة) even though Rasool Allah ﷺ was not there.
So, why, what's the reason?
Some scholar said; Because of its huge importance, it was given this honorary title of being Ghazwa(غزوة)
even though Rasool Allah ﷺ was not there.
And this is the largest of Sarayah(سراية),
because Sarayah(سراية) like we have seen in the past were small in number
I mean a few hundred max, sometimes it would be as small as four or five would be a Sariyyah(سرية).
But here we have 3000.
There's a Hadith(حديث) in At-Tirimdhi(ألترمذي),
however this Hadith(حديث) is Munqatah(منقطة),
and Munqata(منقطة) is one of the types of weak Hadith(حديث).
But there is another strong Hadith(حديث) that strengthens it,
even though they're not the same in terms of the wording,
but they are are talking, in principle about the same issue.
This Hadith(حديث) in At-Tirimdhi(ألترمذي) states that
Rasool Allah ﷺ sent out an army and among the members of this army
would designate to go out with this army, was Abdullah Bin Rawaha رضي الله عنه
and this army was to leave on Friday
and Ibn Kathir(اِبْنِ كَثِيْر) he mentions this Hadith(حديث) as evidence that
the Muslims left out Madina in Ghazwat Maota(غزوة المؤته) on a Friday.
Abdullah Bin Rawaha(عبدالله بن رواحة) thought about it, he said well I'm one single person
so if I stay because this army was supposed to leave at Fajr(فجر),
if I stay and pray Jumah(جمعه) with Rasool Allah ﷺ,
I will be able to catch up with the army because I'm just one person
because the army as a whole is slow
but one individual can speed up and catch up with the rest.
Rasool Allah ﷺ spotted him in Salah(صلاة),
Rasool Allah ﷺ saw him and said: How come you stayed behind?
Abdullah Bin Rawaha(عبدالله بن رواحة) responded and said: O Messenger of Allah,
اَرَدْتُّ اَنْ اُجَمِّعَ مَعَكْ
I wanted to pray Jumu'ah(جمعه) with you.
Rasool Allah ﷺ told him;
لَوْ اَنْفَقْتَ مَا فِيْ الْاَرْضِ جَمِيْعًا مَا اَدْرَكْتَ غَدْوَتَهُمْ
If you spend all the money on earth you would not catch up with them these few hours
where Abdullah Bin Rawaha(عبدالله بن رواحة) stayed behind between Fajr(فجر) and Jumu'ah(جمعه).
Rasool Allah ﷺ is telling him, if you spend all the money in the world,
you will not catch up with him in terms of reward.
We're not talking about if he stays behind completely.
We're talking about if he catches up with them.
Those few hours that he missed,
he will never be able to make them up even if he spent all the money in the world.
The authentic Hadith(حديث) which I was talking about that witnesses for this Hadith(حديث),
is the saying of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
لَغَدْوَةٌ اَوْ رَوْحَةْ فِيْ سَبِيْلِ الله خَيْرٌ مِنَّ الدُّنْيَا وَمَا فِيْهَا
Leaving early with an army or coming back with them is better than the Earth and everything in it.
Now, let's think about this for a moment,
why did Abdullah Bin Rawaha(عبدالله بن رواحة) stayed behind
he didn't want to stay behind because of fear.
He didn't want to leave Jihad(جهاد) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله).
That wasn't the case.
He had the right intentions for staying behind the wanted to seek knowledge
and seek knowledge from who not from a Shaikh(شيخ) or a great scholar,
he wanted to seek knowledge from Rasool Allah ﷺ himself.
He wanted to stay behind to receive the Ajr(أجر) of Jumu'ah(جمعه)
and Jumu'ah(جمعه) with who with Muhammadﷺ.
Nevertheless, Rasool Allah ﷺ is telling him that what you did is wrong.
Those few hours that you missed, nothing can make them up for you.
So Rasool Allah ﷺ was teaching the Sahabah(صحابه) a lesson
that you are not excused from staying behind.
We know that fighting Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله) can be with yourself.
It can be with your wealth, or it can be with your tongue, because Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
جَاهِدُوا الْمُشْرِكِيْنَ بِاَنْفُسِكُمْ وَ اَمْوَالِكُمْ وَاَلْسِنَتِكُمْ
Fight the disbelievers with yourself and your wealth, and your tongues.
However, fighting the Mushrikeen(مشركين) with ones, tongue alone is not enough.
Otherwise, it would have been sufficient for the great scholars among the Sahabah(صحابه),
to sit behind in Madina and not go out with Rasool Allah ﷺ,
but we know that the scholars of the Sahabah(صحابه) like, Obaye Ibn Ka'ab(أبي إبن كعب) and Muadh Bin Jabal(معاذ إبن جبل)
and the poet of the Sahabah(صحابه) Hassaan Ibn Thabit(حسان بن ثابت),
they all went out in the Ghazawaat(غزوات),
and their knowledge was not an excuse for them to stay behind.
In fact, Rasool Allah ﷺ himself, whom the Ummah(امة) depends on for learning the revelation, he did not stay behind, and he said,
that I wish that I can join with every army that leaves.
Uthman Ibn Affan(عثمان ابن عفان), and Abdur Rahman Ibn Auf(عبدالرحمن بن عوف), who used to finance the armies,
this support by their wealth was not sufficient, for them, they had to go out themselves.
And no one tried to justify and make sense of this by saying that,
well, if they go out they would be killed.
Therefore it's better for them to stay behind and just support with their wealth.
No they had to go out themselves.
And here Rasool Allah ﷺ is telling Abdullah Bin Rawaha(عبدالله بن رواحة)
that no matter what you do, you will not catch up with them.
Even though you prayed Jumu'ah(جمعه) with me,
even though you stayed behind with the intention of learning, Talab-Ul-Ilm(طلب العلم),
that's not an excuse, you should have went out.
The army reached to As-sham(ألشام) to Jordan, present the Jordan.
And they received intelligence that the Romans have heard, of their marching
and they have mobilized an army.
Now, the news that they received wasn't really that good.
If they receive news that the army that, they are meeting
would be an army of 3000 like them, that would have been fine.
If they received intelligence that the Army's twice their numbers 6000 that would be fine.
In fact, we might speculate if they received the news
the army is 10 times their number, such as 30,000.
They would be fine with that.
These are the Sahabah(صحابه) of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
courage and bravery and Eeman(إيمان) and Tawakkul(توكل) on Allah.
But the news was that they are facing an army of 200,000 strong,
100,000 Roman soldiers, professional Roman soldiers,
in addition to 100,000 Christian Arabs, these are the allies of the Romans in the land of As-sham(ألشام).
This is disastrous news.
3000 facing 200,000.
I mean, so far the Muslims have never ever heard of such numbers.
In the past, the largest force that they would face,
for example, in the Battle of Al-Khandaq(ألخندق) was 10,000.
Here they're facing an army of 200,000.
And then, who are we talking about?
We're talking about the soldiers of the Roman Empire.
I mean, they had a reputation.
The Romans and the Persians had the reputation of having strong fighting forces, well trained, well armed, professional soldiers.
We're not talking about tribesmen, we're talking about the professional army.
So, this issue demanded the Shura'a(شورى).
So the Ameer(أمير) Zaid Ibn Harissa(زيد بن حارثه) consulted with the prominent Sahabah(صحابه).
What should we do?
Some of them said let's send messenger to Rasool Allah ﷺ,
and ask him what should be done well, let's, let's wait.
Abdullah Bin Rawaha رضي الله عنه said;
Men, what you dislike is what you have come forth to seek, martyrdom.
Listen to this, Men, what do you dislike is what you have come forth to seek.
Abdullah Bin Rawaha(عبدالله بن رواحة) is reminding them with their original intentions,
you are companions of Rasool Ullah, you came out with the intention.
Every one of you every single one of you wants to die Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله),
that's our ultimate goal, ultimate desire.
If that is what we want, how come now we are disliking it.
I mean, what is the reason, you're asking us to pause and wait?
What is the reason you're asking us to not face the enemy?
Is it fear of death?
Well, what's the point in that we all came here with the intention of dying Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله).
So, he reminded them.
وَذَكِّرْ فَاِنَّ الذِّكْرَىٰ تَنْفَعُ الْمُؤمِنِيْنْ
Remind them because the reminder will benefit the believers,
Abdullah Bin Rawaha(عبدالله بن رواحة) then told them.
We are not fighting by means of our numbers or strength,
we are combating them only with this religion, with which Allah has honored us.
Go forth, it will only result in one of the two good outcomes, either victory or martyrdom.
اِحْدَ الْحُسْنَيَيْنْ اِمَّاالنَّصْرُ وَاِمَّا الشَّهَادَةْ
This is what every Muslim looks up to, either to to win against the enemy in Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) or die Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله).
That encouraged them and they said: By Allah, Ibn Rawaha(إبن رواحة) is right.
And they decided to go forth, no matter what the consequences are.
And this tells us about the spirit of the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم.
Their thoughts, their concern was with Aakhira(آخرة).
That's what they were concerned about! Aakhira(آخرة) and not Duniyah(دُنِيَّا).
And we are facing Allahعَزّوجَلّ, let's go on the other side of this Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) will be meeting Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
وَصَلَّى الله عَلى سَيَّدِنَا محمد وَعَلى اَلِهِ وَ صَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًا كَثِيْرًا